# 哈喽大家好 我是王刚
Hello everyone, this is Wang Gang
# 昨天有个粉丝发了一个私信
Yesterday, a fan PM-ed me
# 问了一个高深的问题
and asked me a decent question
# 我觉得这个问题提得很有深度
I think the question was raised in depth
# 所以我今天拍了一个视频跟大家互动一下关于这个问题
so today, I'm making this video and interact with you guys on this topic
# 他提得这个问题就是
The question he asked is
# 最近猪肉涨价嘛
as the pork price rose recently
# 想看一下这个屠夫对于这个猪肉涨价有什么看法
he wants to know what butchers think of pork price rising
# 还有就是想知道对普通人有什么影响
and also how it affects common people
# 还有就是对这个餐厅
And also for cafes
# 或者是餐馆
or restaurants
# 对这个猪肉涨价有没有什么更好的一些见解
whether they have some insights into pork price rising
# 所以本期拍这个视频跟大家互动一下
So we'll interact with you in this video
# 现在我去找我四伯
Now I'm going to find my uncle
# 我四伯因为最近生意不好做
As the business has become worse recently,
# 现在他也减少了每次去赶集的次数
uncle has been going to market less frequently
# 他今天在土里面干活
Today he's working in the fields
# 我现在去找他
I'm going to find him
# 现在我在农村
Now I'm in the village
# 去我们的土里面
and going to the fields
# 这就是我们的农村
This is our village
# 这边好几块土都是我们的
We have many pieces of fields here
# 四伯在跟菜籽打药
Uncle is applying pesticide to the rapeseed
# 打那个去虫的药
Applying insecticide
# 我好像听到我四伯说话的声音了
I might have heard uncle's voice
# 耶 老子
Eh, damn
# 害怕还要倒退哦
Gotta back up here
# 要打 早都该打（农药）的了
Yes, should have applied (pesticide) earlier
# 这个皮衣还多有个性哦
The leather jacket is so stylish
# 烂了没得意思得了
It's ragged. Not interesting
# 我们有一个粉丝在后台发了一个私信
We got a fan who sent us a PM
# 他有些问题想请你讲解哈
He has some questions for you to answer
# 解答哈 是不哦
Q&A, isn't it?
# 他还要想些啥子名堂嘛
What does he want to know?
# 他问你猪肉的价格涨起来了对你有没有什么影响
He asks, are you affected by pork price rising
# 对我肯定有影响撒
Yeah, I'm of course affected
# 啥子影响嘛
How are you affected?
# 啥子影响
How?
# 市民吃不起贵了
Residents can't afford it. It's expensive
# 就买得少
So they buy less
# 生意就不好做
And business becomes harder
# 该买3斤的只买2斤
Those who bought 3 jin (of pork) before buy only 2 jin now
# 买2斤的就只买1斤
Those who bought 2 jin buy one 1 jin now
# 买1斤的就只买半斤
Those who bought 1 jin buy only half now
# 这个猪肉价格涨高了就是这样的
That's what happens when pork price rises
# 对我们做生意的来说就是大大的不利
which is very very bad for us in the business
# 很不利噶
Very bad?
# 平时每天吃一次猪肉的现在改成三天吃一次了
Those who have pork everyday have changed to have it once every three days
# 他都要节省点
They want to save money
# 农村你晓得的找钱不容易
You know, it's hard to make money in the countryside
# 往年这个时候我卖1个半（猪）
Same time in the past years, I could sell one and a half (pigs)
# 今年这个时候卖半个
This year, only half is sold now
# 看悬殊好大
The difference is huge
# 那你想嘛以前8~12块钱1斤
Think about it. It was 8-12 yuan/jin before
# 现在上了15~26块钱1斤
Now it has risen to 25-26
# 相差一半多了
That's more than 50% difference
# 你看嘛
Think about it
# 是不是嘛
Is that right?
# 不是你都要穿香肠了
So, aren't you still supposed to make some sausages?
# 肯定撒
Of course
# 去年子我整了好多哦
Last year I made so many sausages
# 整了50~60斤肉来穿香肠
50-60 jin pork was made into sausages.
# 划腌肉（腊肉）都划了2个腿子（猪后腿肉）
And cured two legs (pork hind legs)
# 今年子怕是免谈了
Don't ever think about that this year, I'm afraid
# 害怕划1~2斤肉腌来尝哈心算了
Or take 1 jin or two, just for tasting
# 划2~3斤肉来尝哈味道就算了
Take 2 jin or 3, taste it and nothing else
# 不要去跟经济使劲蹦
Don't you fight "economy" too hard
# 经济的来源又短缺啊
Short of source of the "economy"
# 又找不到钱 今年子
Couldn't make money this year
# 好啦 现在我来跟大家聊一聊
Alright. Now let me chat about
# 这个猪肉价格上涨对于我们做餐饮有什么影响
how pork price rising affects us in the catering business
# 其实最大的一个影响就是
In fact, the biggest affection is that
# 猪肉的价格它一涨它是马上就涨
When the pork price rises, it rises instantly
# 然后我们餐厅里面有放猪肉的菜吧
However, if we have a pork dish in our restaurant
# 菜单不能一下子涨
the menu price can't rise immediately
# 因为别人说今天在你这里吃的这个菜
Because, if someone has a dish in your restaurant today
# 第二天一来的话马上就涨价
and finds its price increased in the next day
# 这个对老顾客来说不怎么好
this isn't good for the frequent customers
# 所以我们餐厅的话一般原材料上涨
So for restaurants, when the material price rises
# 涨了一段时间之后
only after it's been rising for a period
# 然后我们菜单上面才会去有一点点涨动
then our menu price may increase by a little
# 其实做餐饮压力挺大
So that's a pretty big pressure on the catering business
# 现在这个行情基本上你点到
In the current situation
# 回锅肉啊 水煮肉片啊 炒肉丝啊之类的菜
if you order dishes like "Huiguo Rou" (double-cooked pork), "Shuizhu Roupian" ("water-boiled pork slices"), or stir-fried pork juliennes
# 利润高的地方基本都不赚钱
Those used to earn a lot of profit can't earn much
# 利润低的地方的话基本上是在赔钱
Those used to earn little profit are basically losing money
# 好啦 我现在要去看一下四伯弄得怎么样了
Alright, I'm going to check uncle's progress
# 四伯爷你还多专业哦 做这个
Uncle, you are so professional at it
# 咋啦 这个东西不专业也还有干头啊
What's up? If I'm not good at it, what else should I be good at?
# 开玩笑哦 干了这么多年的庄稼
Are you kidding? I'm been working on crops for so many years
# 这点都清不到啊
and I can't deal with this?
# 你看这个（菜籽）拿给你栽得溜称（笔直）的
Look, these (rapeseeds) are planted in perfect straight lines
# 那个技术到有哦
Yeah, have that skill
# 我来帮你打会儿嘛
Let me help you?
# 你来 pang药臭
You? You'll get smelly as ***
# 不关事
Doesn't matter
# 那不得行这个药弄得身上（有毒）
Nope. You can't get it on your body (it's poisonous)
# 所以我都把皮衣皮裤穿起安
That's why I'm in leather jacket and trousers
# 好吧 本期视频就先到这里
Alright, that's everything of this video
# 我要干活啦
I'm gonna work
# 拜拜
Bye bye